<?xml-stylesheet href="/rss.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Garrett Byrd</title><link>https://garrettbyrd.net/</link><description>Recent content on Garrett Byrd</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2025 Garrett Byrd</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://garrettbyrd.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I Bought a $500 Donkey Kong Machine</title><link>https://garrettbyrd.net/blog/post2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://garrettbyrd.net/blog/post2/</guid><description>Garrett Byrd https://garrettbyrd.net/blog/post2/ -&lt;p>Yes, I bought a Switch 2. I paid $534.99 including tax at my local Target. I got the last one, so sorry to all the kids who got there after about 5:15pm today.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I really don&amp;rsquo;t play the original Switch much at all. That machine stays at my parents&amp;rsquo; house and we ocassionally use it to play &lt;em>Mario Kart 8&lt;/em> when I visit family (and truth be told on this, I&amp;rsquo;m really more of a &lt;em>Mario Party&lt;/em> guy).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To drag this point out even further, I don&amp;rsquo;t even play games that much even more. I don&amp;rsquo;t say this with any kind of pride; I do love interactive narratives, and there are countless wonderful experiences that are on my video game bucket list. (This is not to praise products like Fortnite, League of Legends, or Call of Duty. These are soulless experiences designed to get children addicted to gambling.) Still, I left work this Monday evening and headed straight to Best Buy (which was expectedly out of stock) and then to Target to acquire the latest Nintendo hardware.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Is it overpriced? No, not really. The Sony PS3 released for $500 in 2006 (that&amp;rsquo;s nearly $800 in 2025 $USD, granted it did play a dual-role as a Blu-Ray player), and console prices have floated around $400-$500 ever since. The Switch 2 costs $450, $500 to get &lt;em>Mario Kart World&lt;/em> included.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Are the games overpriced? Yeah, probably. Still, it&amp;rsquo;s a miracle that the $60 standard for a new game has lasted this long. That&amp;rsquo;s been the standard since the late 90s (citation needed); adjusting for inflation, that&amp;rsquo;s about $30 for a new game in 2005 money. No wonder AAA studios are packing their products with more micro-transactions than an amoeba&amp;rsquo;s garage sale. My point here is not that my heart is bleeding for these piece of shit companies (fuck you Blizzard, Konami, Ubisoft, and all the others except maybe From Software). My point is that I&amp;rsquo;m shocked that major game releases haven&amp;rsquo;t jumped in price sooner. $80 for &lt;em>Mario Kart&lt;/em>? Not for me, but I was fortunate enough to functionally get it for $50 as part of the bundle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$70 for Donkey Kong? When I say &amp;ldquo;fuck you&amp;rdquo; to AAA studios, of course this includes Nintendo. The company has a long history of fighting its patrons in many different ways. One of the more upsetting is there continual fight against the archiving and documentation of discontinued products, though Nintendo is hardly unique in this regard. As I&amp;rsquo;ll mention below, they also struggle to properly credit their creative staff. So why am I indulging in the $70 premium for a new title? Well, I&amp;rsquo;m not particularly proud of that induglence, but what can I say? I like Donkey Kong. (Also there are some other titles, including &lt;em>Kirby Air Riders&lt;/em> and &lt;em>Totally Not Bloodborne 2&lt;/em> that I&amp;rsquo;ll be picking up.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What&amp;rsquo;s it like actually playing on the damn thing? It&amp;rsquo;s nice. It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful piece of hardware, and it might have the nicest screen I&amp;rsquo;ve ever purchased. The colors are colorful, the blacks are black, etc., etc. I was actually shocked to learn that it&amp;rsquo;s not an OLED screen, it really does look nice for an LCD. The buttons are clicky as hell, the joysticks are comfortable (give it a year or two to see if the stick drift problem re-emerges), and the built-in stand is great. So far, I actually fold out the stand whole I hold it in my hands for further support. To detach the joycons, there&amp;rsquo;s a simple button/lever combo that feels super nice; the magnets are &lt;em>firm&lt;/em>, which makes it super satisfying to attach/detach them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So how are the games? Well, I haven&amp;rsquo;t purchased any. As mentioned, I did get a digital copy of &lt;em>Mario Kart World&lt;/em>, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t even redeemed it yet. How about the new Donkey Kong game? That doesn&amp;rsquo;t come out until next month! But I still haven&amp;rsquo;t lied with my title. The first and only game I&amp;rsquo;ve played so far is &lt;em>Donkey Kong Country&lt;/em>, which I played through the virtual SNES software on the Switch 2.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Damn, it felt good to sit on the couch and play a video game. I made it through the first world of DKC (&lt;em>Kongo Jungle&lt;/em>), stopping after having beaten the first boss, &lt;em>Very Gnawty&lt;/em>. This game is a masterpiece, and playing it on my couch in my living room on a big TV transported me away from the desk/chair/monitor setup I&amp;rsquo;m accustomed to (in the best of ways). The three &lt;em>Donkey Kong Country&lt;/em> games were some of the first games I played as a young boy. Born in &amp;lsquo;99, I actually had these available in conjunction with many Nintendo 64 titles. These cartridges included, naturally, &lt;em>Donkey Kong 64&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>DKC and DK64 are near and dear to my heart. Their influence on my musicianship cannot be overstated. David Wise (DKC) and Grant Kirkhope (DK64) are wonderful composers who have influenced many in the video game composition world, and Nintendo have demonstrated disregard for them by not crediting these composers for their contributions in later works. E.g., Kirkhope&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>DK Rap&lt;/em> was used in the Mario movie without credits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although I majored in applied math, I also minored in music theory during my undergraduate studies. My senior year, I was fortunate enough to work with a wonderful member of the music department faculty at UTK under whom I took an independent study course for my final music theory credits. I can&amp;rsquo;t recall the exact name of the project, but the thesis was a comprison of the composition techniques of Wise and Kirkhope in &lt;em>Donkey Kong Country&lt;/em> and &lt;em>Donkey Kong 64&lt;/em> that highlighted some more complex techniques utilized by Kirkhope (namely the usage of &amp;ldquo;adaptive music&amp;rdquo;), which mirrored the complexity of a 3D game compared to a 2D game.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could ramble for too long about the&amp;hellip; &lt;em>difficulties&lt;/em>&amp;hellip; of DK64. I recommend Dunkey&amp;rsquo;s playthrough of the game; Dunkey is a beyond-charming, long-time internet personality, and his struggles during this playthrough highlight many of the game&amp;rsquo;s pain points. Nevertheless, it should suffice to say that, despite its flaws, the only &lt;em>real&lt;/em> 3D Donkey Kong game fills my soul with nostalgia for polygonal apes and low-resolution banana textures. This is the crux of my $500 Donkey Kong Machine. On July 17, &lt;em>Donkey Kong Bonanza&lt;/em> is being released for the Switch 2, and I&amp;rsquo;ll be there to give DK&amp;rsquo;s new design for a spin.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Is Nintendo a huge, money-hungry company? Oh yeah. But do their games still have soul? For me, yes. They&amp;rsquo;re pretty regularly trying new things, &lt;em>occasionally&lt;/em> showing love to older gems, such as the &lt;em>Paper Mario: The Thousand Year Door&lt;/em> remake (that remake had so much love and respect poured into it), and demonstrate some level of quality and charm in their works. Their shit usually &lt;em>runs&lt;/em> at launch, which is a depressingly low bar to set. At least, this is compared to the likes of Microsoft, Sony, Epic, Riot, and others who produce the video game equivalents of Chicken McNuggets. (More precisely, Chicken McNuggets that are sold through a subscription service&amp;hellip; with the option to pay extra for blinking lights on the cardboard box.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyway, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna go play more &lt;em>Donkey Kong Country&lt;/em> on my $500 lobotomized SNES.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Primate games are fun. Thanks for reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>GB&lt;/p>
- https://garrettbyrd.net/blog/post2/ - 2025 Garrett Byrd</description></item><item><title>A First Post</title><link>https://garrettbyrd.net/blog/post1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://garrettbyrd.net/blog/post1/</guid><description>Garrett Byrd https://garrettbyrd.net/blog/post1/ -&lt;p>Although this initial post will be without much substance, I&amp;rsquo;d figured that getting &lt;em>something&lt;/em> up onto the site would grease the wheels for further thoughts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am at a point where I very much enjoy blogs. Without mentioning the buzz word to end all buzz words (that two-letter intialism), I&amp;rsquo;ll emphasize that the value of human expression is at a local maximum. Humans need to create things, get things wrong, and have discussions with other humans.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I think back to how I have felt about blogs throughout my life, there are really three main phases (if I am being overly structured). &amp;ldquo;Phase 1&amp;rdquo; would be my early childhood. Growing up in the 00s, I was fortunate enough to be child in a world which was still coasting off of the cultural optimism of the nineties. Along with this came the perspective of watching the rapid development of technology. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I had an accurate perspective on what a &amp;ldquo;blog&amp;rdquo; actually was, moreso imagery deriving from &lt;em>Zoey 101&lt;/em> and similar television shows. That is, a blog was something a teenage girl would use to talk about music and boys, not something for any kind of technical discussion. In retrospect, there were a variety of sites which I would frequent which were essentially individuals talking about things they enjoy, find interesting, etc. Among these was &lt;a href="https://www.dragonflycave.com">dragonflycave.com&lt;/a>, which I am glad to see is still up. The site discussed various Pokemon-related things; e.g., providing in-game sprites and a tutorial on sprite &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.dragonflycave.com/spriting-guide">splicing&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; (e.g., putting the arms of a geodude onto a voltorb).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Phase 2&amp;rdquo; would be my teenage years, up until about the end of grad school. My only real opinion I held during this time was the blogs are part of &amp;ldquo;the old internet&amp;rdquo;, an idea which I had a respect for, but did not long for in the way I do now. The final phase would be where I am at now. The internet is a terrible, commercial place. Finding a site where someone is explaining something technical, or even expressing an opinion in greater than 140 characters is an oasis in the desert.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have found your way to my tiny corner, please consider blogging in any way/shape/form. Use substack, make a static site with hugo (the source code for this site can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/garrdbyrd/site/tree/main">here&lt;/a>, go ahead and use it), hell, use SquareSpace or WordPress. Express an idea in a medium/long format. Tell the world about an album you listened to, or the latest, weirdest meal you&amp;rsquo;ve made for dinner, write a short bit of fiction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Human ideas are valuable. Thanks for reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>GB&lt;/p>
- https://garrettbyrd.net/blog/post1/ - 2025 Garrett Byrd</description></item></channel></rss>